Guide to the Romance Languages and Literature Department records, 1958-1992 RG0080
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Romance Languages and Literature Department records
1958-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Dept. of Romance Languages and Literature
RG0080
8.75 Linear Feet
Collection includes graduate student exams and manuscript preparation, correspondence, photos, programs, publications, audio cassettes.
Restrictions on Access
Series 3 is closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation. Any student records in the collection, such as those in Series 1, are closed to research until the death of the student.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from Romance Languages and Literature Department.
Historical or Biographical Note
The George Washington University's Department of Romance Languages and Literatures is composed of faculty members who teach courses in Spanish, French, Italian and Portuguese. The Department has been known as Romance Languages and Literatures since 1933, before that it was known as Romance Languages.
The Department fosters the reflective study of these cultures as well as a critical awareness of the complex ties that exist among Europe, Latin America, Africa, the Caribbean, and North America. They teach all levels of Spanish, French, and Italian language and literature, as well as first- and second-year Portuguese. The Department views language, culture and literature as complementary aspects of a single mission. Faculty members' scholarship and teaching enrich each other and lead to innovative approaches in the courses offered. The department pursues the model of a multi-cultural and multi-disciplinary intellectual community. The Department nourishes the geographical and cultural richness of Washington, DC and promotes the process of lifelong learning from both global and interactive perspectives.
Faculty are deeply committed to the critical analysis of literature, culture and film. Many faculty members also participate in Interdisciplinary programs at the graduate level, such as the Latin American Studies Program and the Graduate Program in the Human Sciences. The Department offers a wide variety of courses in literature and culture. Introductory courses in French, Italian and Spanish Literature are regularly offered, as well as courses dedicated to specific periods, authors or Special topics. Courses on film and cross-cultural studies are an important part of our curriculum. The department requires all majors to take a one-year seminar in advanced literature and criticism in preparation for the major field examination. This course marks the culmination of students' knowledge of language, literature and culture.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include graduate student exams and manuscript preparation, correspondence, photos, programs, publications, audio cassettes, Financial Committee information, and the St. Gall exhibit (Dr. James King). They range in date from 1962-88, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Chair of the Romance Languages and Literature Department. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Graduate student exams and manuscript preparation; Fellowships, grants, and NDEA; Financial Committee, Division of History; St. Gall (Switzerland) exhibit and conference materials; and Writings, newspapers, and publications.
Exhibitions; Examinations; Publications; Audiocassettes; Washington (D.C.); King, James Cecil; George Washington University
- Graduate student exams and manuscript preparation, 1962-1988; RG0080 Series 1; 4.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains graduate student exams and manuscript preparation in the Romance Languages and Literature Department from 1962 to 1988.
  - Amir, Alikhani, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bajuk, Catalina, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barazzone, Alexandra, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bele, Sally A., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bell, Nan J., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beneke, Susan E., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bernoussi, Fakid, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Breiner- Saunders, Karen, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bufill, Jose' A., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Capella, Anne, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Christophe, Marc, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clark, Beatrice, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cline, Alanna G., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Collings, Karen, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Davis, Carolyn, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dexter, Robert P., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ely, Marvin T., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Finocchiaro, Lucia, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fornasa, Giuliano, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gasster, Susan, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gersternberg, Faunchon, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Godman, Anne, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Greenfield, Yvonne C., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Grenier, Joan, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Harmon, Danute, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hartman, Sister Elanor, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hattendorf, Richard, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Heuston, Carlyn H., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ianotta, Philomena B., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Ibacache, Maria L., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jackson, Shirley M., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Jordon, Jack, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Karas, Peter, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Kazanjian, Ani, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Keimowitz, Hazel, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Kinginger, Celeste, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - LeBeau, Francis-Paul, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - LePage, Raymond G., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lindquist, Hilda, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Lister, Aleta, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mackie, Therese, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Manelbaum, Laurie C., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Karachi, Catherine, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Matsen, Anne Lovell, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Maull, Cynthia, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - McBride, Margaret, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - McConnell, A.R., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - McLaughlin, Mary, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Morrison, Helena H., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Moser, Anastasia, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Mucciante, Maryse A., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Packman, Wendy, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pinell, Veronica, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Prendergast, Sister Maria, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Prendergast, Sister Maria, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Quann, Joanna L., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Roberts, Nancy, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Shapiro, Jenny, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Smith, James B., Jr., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Soudee, Madeline M., 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Staunton, Cheryl, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Steinberg, Marie, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Stillman, Linda K. (Klieger), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Todd, Mary Ann, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Van der Branden, Yves, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Wall, Nancy, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ward, Monique, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Weiss, Marcia, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Weld, Patriciaa, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Williams, John, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Witt, Donald, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ziolkowski, Corrine S., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Zola Manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Zola Proof 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Zola Final Galley, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Hugo Manuscript, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hugo Manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hugo Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Hugo Revisions, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hugo Annotated Manuscripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hugo Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Moral and Humanitarian Dimensions of Hugo's Les Miserables, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Fellowships, grants, and NDEA, 1958-1974; RG0080 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series contains correspondence, reports, government publications, an invitation, brochures, a poster, and a bulletin. They range in date from 1958 to 1974. They concern a research grant; requirements for a degree; the National Defense Education Act (NDEA), Public Law 85-864; "Higher Education and National Affairs"; the American Council on Education; and NDEA fellowships for the Romance Language and Literature, the Germanic Language and Literature, and the Institutes for Teachers in Counseling and Guidance.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is currently missing.
  - Government Subsidized Programs For Graduate Study--National Defense Education Act, 1958-60, 09/02/1958 -12/13/1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Government Subsidized Programs For Graduate Study - National Defense Education Act, 1961-62, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Romance Languages and Literatures, 01/13/1969 -06/01/1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Financial Committee, Division of History, RG0080 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains materials from the Financial Committee, Division of History.
- St. Gall (Switzerland) exhibit and conference materials from Dr. James King, 1992; RG0080 Series 4; 2 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 3, Box 1, Box 4)
  This series contains exhibit and conference correspondence, photographs, programs, and audio cassettes from James King and the St. Gall (Switzerland) exhibit and conference in 1992.
  - Correspondence and documentation [1/2], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and documentation [2/2], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Publisher's contract and Correspondence regarding volume, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - German text of exhibition, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - English text of exhibition, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Finances [1/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Finances [2/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proposal submitted to NEH: 1/12/90, 01/12/1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Original Manuscript submitted for publication: 8/21/92, 08/21/1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Original Manuscript con't, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Original Manuscript con't, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - First Interim Report on Exhibition, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Second Interim Report on Exhibition, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Conference Registration and Attendance, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Conference registration slips, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit guides (english and german) and invitation, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Conference programs, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book: La Cultura De La Abadia De Sankt Gallen, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence concerning photos in book, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photocopies of photos for volume, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Permission for illustrations, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photos: Steiner, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    General note
    5 photos, originals used in volume
  - Photos: Ochsenbein, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    4 photos, originals used in volume
  - Photos: Nees, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    19 photos, originals used in volume
  - Photos: Vogler, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    13 photos, originals used in volume
  - Photos: Eggenberger, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Originals used in volume
  - Photos: Notker Balbulus, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photos: Pictures 3-13, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photos: Illustrations 5,7,8,9,11, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photos: Eigenhandige Professeintrage von St. Galler Monchen de 9./10. Jh., undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photos: Stiftsarchiv St. Gallen, Professbuch, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photos: Die St. Galler Stiftskirche, erbaut 1755-1766, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photos: Unidentified slides and negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Writings, newspapers, and publications, ca. 1960-1969; RG0080 Series 5; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains writings, newspapers, and publications from the Romance Languages and Literature Department from the 1960s.